A Guide to the Papers of the Minor and Wilson Family, 1764-1936 (bulk 1800-1936)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Minor and Wilson Family 1764-1936 (bulk 1800-1936)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-602, 3750, 3750-a
This collection consists of 25,000 items (25 feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Minor and Wilson Family Papers were a bequest of Susan Colston Wilson of Charlottesville, Virginia, on December 14, 1981.
Scope and Content Information
The Minor and Wilson family papers consist of ca. 25,000 items (57 Hollinger boxes and one oversize folder, ca. 20 linear shelf feet), 1764, 1783, 1797, 1800-1936, primarily correspondence, diaries, financial and legal papers, speeches, essays, manuscripts, memorabilia, bound volumes, and miscellaneous related papers of the family. Other families represented include Blackford, Colston, Davis, Maury, and Trueheart. Topics of interest in the correspondence include: the Whig Convention of 1844, free public education in Virginia, the temperance movement in Virginia, the American Colonization Society, the Virginia Secession convention of 1861, the Civil War, the University of Virginia, the Virginia Female Institute, 1879, and World War I.
Prominent correspondents include William Alexander Anderson, American Association for the Advancement of Science, Kemp Plummer Battle, Benjamin Lewis Blackford, Charles Minor Blackford, Launcelot Minor Blackford, Mary Berkeley (Minor) Blackford, William Mathews Blackford, Montgomery Blair, Charles Bonnycastle, John Albert Broadus, Albert Gallatin Brown, Joseph Bryan, George Craighead Cabell, James Lawrence Cabell, Joseph Carrington Cabell, Clement Claiborne Clay, Henry Clay, John Hartwell Cocke, Ellas Nelson Conway, Edward Henry Courtenay, John Warwick Daniel, John Anthony Gardner Davis, John Staige Davis, Theodore Dwight, Thomas Harding Ellis, Charles James Faulkner, William Fleming, William Frazier, Muscoe Russell Hunter Garnett, Basil Lanneau Gildersleeve, Thomas Walker Gilmer, Edward Christian Glass, Armistead Churchill Gordon, T.M. Gunter, Ralph Randolph Gurley, James Guthrie, Gessner Harrison, C.P. Hastings, James Philemon Holcombe, Frederick William Mackey Holiday, George Frederick Holmes, Marmaduke Johnson, George Junkin, James Keith, James Christian Lamb, Shelton Farrar Leake, Robert Edward Lee, William Minor Lile, James Russell Lowell, Cyrus H. McCormick, William Holmes McGuffey, Dabney Herndon Maury, Richard Lancelot Maury, Socrates Maupin, Richard Kidder Meade, John Singleton Mosby, William Barclay Napton, George Wharton Pepper, George Wythe Randolph, John Randolph, Wilson Cary Nicholas Randolph, Alexander Rives, William Cabell Rives, William Joseph Robertson, Wyndham Robertson, William Barton Rogers, John Edwin Roller, William Henry Ruffner, Maxmilian Schele deVere, James Alexander Seddon, Eli S. Shorter, Philip Slaughter, Campbell Bascom Slempt, Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart, James Joseph Sylvester, John Reuben Thompson, George W. Trueheart, Henry St. George Tucker, Charles Scott Venable, Richard N. Venable, Frank N. Watkins, Egbert Reed Watson, Daniel Webster, Woodrow Wilson, William Wirt, James Wood, and William Edward Woodruff.
The bulk of the collection consists of papers of John B. Minor (1813-1895), which cover the period ca. 1828-1895. Minor, a University of Virginia law professor, was a son of Launcelot and Mary O. Minor (nee Tompkins). During 1829-1831 he studied at Kenyon College, Gambier, Ohio, and later, at the University of Virginia, and was graduated in 1834 with a Bachelor of Law degree. He began his legal practice in Charlottesville. Minor became professor of law at the University of Virginia in 1845, marrying Nannie F. Colston in 1859 after the death of his first wife. From 1870-1878 he taught a summer course of law lectures that became extremely well-known and respected, and published Institute of Common and Statute Law, as well as Exposition of the Law of Crimes and Punishments in 1894. After the death of his second wife, Minor married Ellen Temple Hill. After fifty years of teaching he died on July 12, 1895.
His papers consist of correspondence, financial and legal papers, essays and speeches, law school papers, printed material, clippings, notebooks, a certificate from Kenyon College, and a University of Virginia diploma.
Most of the remaining papers pertain to Minor's daughters, Susan Colston, Martha (Mattie), and Mary. Susan Colston married John Wilson; her papers, ca. 1890-1931, consist of letters, accounts, printed material, clippings, bound volumes and an unfinished genealogy of her family. Mattie Minor married Conway W. Sams; her papers, ca. 1888-1895, consist of letters to her from friends and relatives, as do Mary Minor's papers, 1865-1907. Other family members with miscellaneous papers include: Lucian Minor, John D. Minor, Kate Temple Minor, Raleigh Colston Minor, Lucy Walker Minor, and Benjamin Blake Minor.
Items of interest in this collection include a copy of a letter from Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico, to Matthew F. Maury, 1866; a 1797 land grant in Albemarle County, Virginia; a reminiscence by William Wertenbaker about Edgar Allan Poe; a copy of the 1878 Students of the University of Virginia catalogue; and an 1853 safe conduct pass for a U.S. ship, Levant.
Organization
The various accessions (38-602, 3750, and 3750-a) have been interfiled in the collection which is arranged chronologically into seven series: I. Correspondence, II. Financial and Legal Papers, III. Speeches and Writings, IV. Law and Miscellaneous School Papers, V. Miscellaneous Papers, Printed Material and Photographs, VI. Bound volumes, and VII. Oversize Material. Items are arranged chronologically within the series. Series I (boxes 1-49) is the largest series and consists of four subseries: general correspondence; correspondence of Susan Colston Minor; letters to Mattie Minor; and miscellaneous single-foldered letters. Series III (Boxes 49A-50) consists chiefly of John B. Minor's writings. Series IV (Boxes 50-51) consists of Minor's papers pertaining to his teaching career in law. Series V (Boxes 51-54) is arranged into four sub- series: miscellaneous papers; printed material; newspaper clippings; and photographs. The bound volumes in Series VI (Boxes 54-56) were numbered and filed chronologically; loose materials in the volumes were placed in numbered paper folders and filed in three manila folders directly after the bound volumes. Item listings of the bound volumes and oversize material are included in the container list appended to this guide.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1764-1835 June, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1835 July-1838 Oct., 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1838 Oct.-1842 Nov., 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1842 Nov.-1844, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1845-1846 Feb., 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1846 Feb.-1850 July., 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1850 Jul.-1953 Jun., 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence 1853 July-1856 Nov., 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Correspondence 1856 Nov.-1861 Sept., 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Correspondence 1861 Sept.-1864 June, 5 folders (Box 10)
  - Correspondence 1864 Aug.-1866, 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Correspondence 1867-1870 Sept., 5 folders (Box 12)
  - Correspondence 1870 Sept.-1872 May, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Correspondence 1872 May-1875 May, 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Correspondence 1875 May-1878 March, 4 folders (Box 15)
  - Correspondence 1878 Apr.-1879 March, 4 folders (Box 16)
  - Correspondence 1879 Apr.-1880 Jan., 4 folders (Box 17)
  - Correspondence 1880 Feb.-Oct., 4 folders (Box 18)
  - Correspondence 1880 Oct.-1882, 4 folders (Box 19)
  - Correspondence 1883-1885 March, 5 folders (Box 20)
  - Correspondence 1885 March-1887, 4 folders (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1888-1890 Oct., 5 folders (Box 22)
  - Correspondence 1890 Oct.-1892 Feb., 5 folders (Box 23)
  - Correspondence 1892 Feb.-Dec., 4 folders (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1892 Dec.-1893, 4 folders (Box 25)
  - Correspondence 1894-, 4 folders (Box 26)
  - Correspondence 1895 Jan.-Aug., 5 folders (Box 27)
  - Correspondence 1895 Aug.-1896 July, 5 folders (Box 28)
  - Correspondence 1896 July-1897 July, 4 folders (Box 29)
  - Correspondence 1897 July-Dec., 5 folders (Box 30)
  - Correspondence 1898-1899, 4 folders (Box 31)
  - Correspondence 1900-1909, 5 folders (Box 32)
  - Correspondence n.d., 4 folders (Box 33)
  - Correspondence n.d., 3 folders (Box 34)
  - Letters of Susan Colston Minor to John Wilson 1890-, 2 folders (Box 34)
  - Letters of Susan Colston Minor to John Wilson 1891-1893, 5 folders (Box 35)
  - Letters of John Wilson to Susan Colston Minor 1890-1893 April, 6 folders (Box 36)
  - Letters of John Wilson to Susan Colston Minor 1893 April-1894, 3 folders (Box 37)
  - Letters to Susan Colston Minor 1893-1895, 2 folders (Box 37)
  - Telegrams of condolence to Mrs. Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1899 (Box 38)
  - Letters to Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1899 (Box 38)
  - Letters to Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1907-1909 (Box 38)
  - Letters to Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1908-1909 (Box 38)
  - Letters of Edmund Minor Wilson to to Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1908 Jan. 28 (Box 38)
  - Letters to Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1908 Dec.-1909 Dec. (Box 38)
  - Letters to Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1909 (Box 38)
  - Letters to Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1910-1911 Oct., 5 folders (Box 39)
  - Letters to Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1911 Oct.-1912, 5 folders (Box 40)
  - Letters to Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1913 Jan.-Oct., 4 folders (Box 41)
  - Letters to Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1913 Dec.-1914 Aug., 5 folders (Box 42)
  - Letters to Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1914 Aug.-1916 Aug., 5 folders (Box 43)
  - Correspondence of Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1918-1919 (Box 44)
  - Letters and related paper re biographical sketch of John Wilson 1922 (Box 44)
  - Letters to Susan Colston Minor Wilson 1923, 1926 & 1931 (Box 44)
  - Letters of Conway W. Sams to Mattie Minor 1887 Feb.-1888 Mar., 3 folders (Box 44)
  - Letters of Conway W. Sams to Mattie Minor 1888 Mar.-1890 Aug. (Box 45)
  - Letters of Conway W. Sams to Mattie Minor 1890 Sept.-Oct. (Box 46)
  - Letters to Mattie Minor Sams 1890 May-Nov., 2 folders (Box 46)
  - Letters of John B. Minor to Mattie Minor Sams 1891-1892 (Box 46)
  - Letters of Mary L. Minor to Mattie Minor Sams 1891-1892 (Box 46)
  - Letters of Nannie Minor to Mattie Minor Sams 1891-1893 (Box 47)
  - Letters of John B. Minor to Mattie Minor Sams 1892-1895 (Box 47)
  - Letters to Mattie Minor Sams 1892-1895 (Box 47)
  - Letters of Mattie Minor Sams to John B. Minor 1892-1895 (Box 47)
  - Letters of Mary L. Minor to Mattie Minor Sams 1893-1894 (Box 47)
  - Letters of Nannie Minor to Mattie Minor Sams 1894-1895 (Box 48)
  - Letters of Mattie Minor Sams to John B. Minor 1895 (Box 48)
  - Letters of Mary L. Minor to Mattie Minor Sams 1895 (Box 48)
  - Letters to Mary L. Minor 1865-1879 (Box 48)
  - Letters to Mary L. Minor 1906-1909, 2 folders (Box 48)
  - William Tompkins to John B. Minor 1835 Jan. 26 (Box 48)
  - Lucian Minor to John B. Minor 1835 Feb. 14 (Box 48)
  - Jeremiah Morton to John B. Minor 1850 Mar.-Jun. (Box 48)
  - Letter and related papers re death of John D. Minor 1851 (Box 48)
  - John Livingston to John B. Minor 1852 Dec. 20 (Box 49)
  - William M. Blackford to John B. Minor 1853 Jan. 5 (Box 49)
  - Letters of John B. Minor to Miss Nannie Colston 1858-1859 (Box 49)
  - Major George W. Carr to John B. Minor 1861-1865 (Box 49)
  - Smith, English & Co. to John B. Minor 1865 (Box 49)
  - Robert E. Lee to John B. Minor 1867 Jan. 17 (Box 49)
  - Prof. Charles Martin to John B. Minor 1870 Sept. 22 (Box 49)
  - Letters of Robert Whittet to John B. Minor 1875-1879 (Box 49)
  - Col. John M. Patton to John B. Minor 1878 Feb. 1 & 17 (Box 49)
  - George S. Patton to John B. Minor 1878 March 18 (Box 49)
  - Charles Cocke to John B. Minor 1879 Jan. 11 (Box 49)
  - Letters of John B. Minor re congratulations on fifty years of teaching 1895 (Box 49)
  - Matthew F. Maury to Launcelot Minor, Sr. 1838 Sept. 24 (Box 49)
  - Matthew F. Maury to Frank Minor 1857 Oct. 13 (Box 49)
  - Matthew F. Maury to Isaac Toucey 1857 Oct. 15 (Box 49)
  - Letters of Matthew F. Maury to John B. Minor 1860-1869 & 1892 (Box 49)
  - Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico, to M.F. Maury (copy) 1866 April 16 (Box 49)
  - H. L. Maury to John B. Minor 1860 May 15 (Box 49)
  - Richard S. Maury to John B. Minor 1860 Aug. 21 (Box 49)
  - William A. Maury to John B. Minor 1866 May 31 (Box 49)
  - Daniel Webster to Thomas Walker Gilmer 1841 June 15 & 18 (Box 49)
  - J. B. Nourse to his parents 1846 July 26 & Aug. 3 (Box 49)
  - J. W. Randolph to John B. Minor 1850 (Box 49)
  - George W. Randolph to John B. Minor 1852 Nov. 20 & 28 (Box 49)
  - Cyrus McCormick to Mary Minor 1867 June 6 (Box 49)
  - Correspondence from commonplace book of Mary G. Minor 1886-1893 (Box 49)
  - Basil L. Gildersleeve to SMW 1921 Feb. 21 (Box 49)
  - Letters to Edmund Minor Wilson 1922-1924 (Box 49)
  - Patsy W. Carr to Martha M. Davis n.d. (Box 49)
  - L.A.M. to Kitty Minor n.d. (Box 49)
  - [Minor] Wilson to [?] Finley n.d. (Box 49)
  - Legal Correspondence of the Hays family 1842 (Box 49)
  - Correspondence re the Civil War and other topics 1861-1878 (Box 49)
- Series II: Financial and legal Papers
  - Financial and Legal Papers 1822-1845, n.d., 2 folders (Box 49)
  - Land Grant, Albemarle County, Virginia to Mourning Roberts 1797 Aug. 1 (Box 49A)
  - Deed, Robert French, Launcelot Minor to Peter Minor 1814 June 1 (Box 49A)
  - Court Record 1820 March 29 (Box 49A)
  - Account of Martha M. Davis with Healy Street & Co. 1830-1831 (Box 49A)
  - Business Papers (Estimates) 1830-1841 (Box 49A)
  - Accounts 1833 (Box 49A)
  - Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery for Botetourt County 1833 (Box 49A)
  - Court Record of Circuit Superior Court of Botetourt County 1834-1835 (Box 49A)
  - Deed, Robert T. Thompson to John B. Minor 1835 March 20 (Box 49A)
  - Deed, George R. Marshall to Hobson 1835 July-1838 Oct. (Box 49A)
  - Deed, James & Elizabeth Hill to John B. Minor 1835 Sept. (Box 49A)
  - Court Record 1835 Oct. 30 (Box 49A)
  - Deed, George A. Marshall to State of Virginia 1836 (Box 49A)
  - Deed, Andrew S. Boyd & Thomas Martin to Robert Thompson 1836 (Box 49A)
  - Bills and Notes (Marshall) 1837-1838 (Box 49A)
  - Account of Dr. Benjamin F. Trice 1838 (Box 49A)
  - Bond of George Wolfe to Sarah Cheatham 1839 June 26 (Box 49A)
  - Court proceedings of Albemarle County Court 1839 Oct. 14 (Box 49A)
  - Committee for Relief of Wounded-list of expenses 1863 July (Box 49A)
  - "List of subscriptions to University Chapel taken from Mrs. John H. Wheeler's Book" 1883-1884 (Box 49A)
  - Sworn statement of John B. Minor 1920 Aug. 18 (Box 49A)
  - Accounts of SMW 1935-1936 (Box 49A)
  - "Rights of Tenants in Common of Mineral Lands" by John Wilson n.d. (Box 49A)
- Series III: Speeches and Writings
  - "Upon Miscellaneous Reading" by John B. Minor 1830 Nov. 20 (Box 49A)
  - Untitled Essay by John B. Minor 1830 Dec. 4 (Box 49A)
  - "Has Criticism Been Beneficial to "Literature?" by John B. Minor 1830 Dec. 18 (Box 49A)
  - "The Influence of Poetry" by John B. Minor 1830-1831 (Box 49A)
  - "Of Incorporeal Hereditaments" by John B. Minor 1830-1831 (Box 49A)
  - "Political Economy" by John B. Minor 1830-1831 (Box 49A)
  - "Political Principle" by John B. Minor 1830-1831 (Box 49A)
  - A Tale of the Revolution 1830-1831 (Box 49A)
  - "The Influence of Poetry" by John B. Minor 1830-1831 (Box 49A)
  - "The Fountain of Character" by John B. Minor 1830-1831 (Box 49A)
  - Essay on Government by John B. Minor 1830-1831 (Box 49A)
  - "Observations on No. 177 of The Spectator" by John B. Minor 1831 Jan. 4 (Box 49A)
  - An oration on "Union" by John B. Minor 1831 Jan. 20 (Box 49A)
  - "Liberty" by John B. Minor 1831 Jan. 22 (Box 49A)
  - "Happiness" by John B. Minor 1831 Feb. 7 (Box 49A)
  - "Why is Advice So Often Disregarded?" by John B. Minor 1831 Feb. 17 (Box 49A)
  - "The Proper Study of Mankind is Man" by John B. Minor 1831 March 5 (Box 49A)
  - "Education" by John B. Minor 1831 April 27 (Box 49A)
  - "Wit" by John B. Minor 1831 May 25 (Box 49A)
  - Essay on Oratory by John B. Minor 1831 June 8 (Box 49A)
  - Address before Ph[ilosophy] Society 1831 June 10 (Box 49A)
  - "Scheme of Studies" by John B. Minor 1836 (Box 49A)
  - Notes for Public Address 1843 (Box 49A)
  - Papers relating to Public Education in Virginia and John B. Minor's interest in it 1845-1849 (Box 49A)
  - Biographical sketch submitted by [?] Minor 1847 (Box 49A)
  - Material pertinent to "The University of Virginia Casket" 1849 (Box 49A)
  - Two poems: "The More Convenient Season" and "The Voice of Free Grace" 1854-1859 (Box 49A)
  - "Last Moments of Beloved John" (John Davis Minor) 1857 Dec. (Box 49A)
  - "Nearing the End," - written for Bishop Wilmer on his 80th birthday 1896 March 15 (Box 49A)
  - Speech before the Bellfreed Church Club on "The Currency" by [?] 1896 (Box 49A)
  - "The Story of a Simple Life" by Elizabeth Maury Coombs 1926, TMs (Box 49A)
  - Synopsis of Proceedings in Chancery by John B. Minor n.d. (Box 49A)
  - Untitled speech by John B. Minor n.d. (Box 49A)
  - Institutes of Common Statute Law by John B. Minor (Pt. II Div. VI, Chapter I in Vol. 4, Pt. 2 of 1876 edition) n.d., AMs (Box 50)
  - Notes for biography of John B. Minor n.d. (Box 50)
  - Biography of [John B. Minor] n.d., TMs (Box 50)
- Series IV: Law and Miscellaneous School Papers
  - Monthly Reports, Questions and Examinations of the School of Law, University of Virginia 1845-1851, 2 folders (Box 50)
  - Law School Moot Court Cases 1845-1849 (Box 50)
  - Law School Grades, Examinations, and Rolls 1852-1858 (Box 50)
  - Law School Grades, Examinations, and Rolls 1859-1861 (Box 51)
  - Law Examination taken by [?] Smith 1870-1875 (Box 51)
  - Examinations in Law 1885 and n.d. (Box 51)
  - Notes for Law Classes n.d. (Box 51)
  - Class Exercises of John D. Minor 1846-1850 (Box 51)
  - Latin Exercises of John Davis Minor 1850-1851 (Box 51)
  - Greek Exercises of John Davis Minor 1850-1851 (Box 51)
  - Greek and Latin Translations, Exercises of John B. Minor n.d. (Box 51)
- Series V: Miscellaneous Papers, Printed Material and Photographs
  - Miscellaneous Civil War Memoranda, etc. 1861-1865 (Box 51)
  - "Exhibiting Actual Receipts and Expenditures - Session 1874-75" 1874-1875 (Box 51)
  - Deposit of John B. Minor in the Library of Congress 1875 (Box 51)
  - Miscellany ca. 1916 (Box 51)
  - Miscellany n.d., 2 folders (Box 51)
  - Miscellaneous Library of Prof. John B. Minor n.d. (Box 52)
  - Recollections of the Edgar Allan Poe years at the University of Virginia by William Wertenbaker n.d. (Box 52)
  - Name list from Mary L. Minor's commonplace book re death and funeral of John B. Minor n.d. (Box 52)
  - Printed Material 1849, 1873, 1893, 1931, & n.d. (Box 52)
  - Printed Material 1850-1920 (Box 52)
  - Printed Material n.d. (Box 52)
  - Bible Examiners 1850 Jan. & June, 2 folders (Box 52)
  - Students of the University of Virginia: A Semi-Centennial Catalogue 1878 (Box 52)
  - John B. Minor by James C. Lamb 1895 Oct. 10 (Box 52)
  - The Lost Cause, United Daughters of the Confederacy Magazine1901 Oct. (Box 52)
  - Releigh Colston Minor(1869-1923) by Robert B. Tunstall 1923 (Box 52)
  - Valentines n.d. (Box 52)
  - Calling Cards n.d. (Box 53)
  - Obituary Notice of Lucy Walker Minor (Mrs. Charles Minor) 1880 (Box 53)
  - Newspaper clippings re death notices of John B. Minor 1895 (Box 53)
  - Newspaper clippings 1895, 1912, n.d. (Box 53)
  - Clippings re Ash Lawn (copy) 1903 (Box 53)
  - Newspaper clippings 1917, 1934, n.d. (Box 53)
  - Newspaper clippings re the death of Warren G. Harding 1923 Aug. (Box 53)
  - Obituary notices of Raleigh C. Minor and Mrs. Susan Colston Blackford 1923 (Box 53)
  - Newspaper clippings 1928, 1930, 1932-1934 (Box 53)
  - "Virginia vs. Harvard in Antebellum Days" 1935 (Box 53)
  - Newspaper Interview of Miss Susan Wilson n.d. (Box 53)
  - Newspaper clippings n.d. (Box 53)
  - Photographs 1890's & n.d. (Box 54)
- Series VI: Bound Volumes
  - Notebook of Martha M. Davis (#1) 1828 (Box 54)
  - "Notes from Anacharsis' travels in Greece" (#2) 1830 (Box 54)
  - Journal and Notebook of John B. Minor (#3) 1831 (Box 54)
  - Chancery notebook [of John B. Minor] (#4) 1844 (Box 54)
  - Memoranda book of John Davis Minor (#5) 1847 (Box 54)
  - Diary of Mary L. Minor (#6) 1852 (Box 54)
  - Notebook of John B. Minor (#7) 1854-1855 (Box 54)
  - "Journal of a Northern Tour," Mary L. Minor (#8) 1859 (Box 54)
  - Notebook of Mary L. Minor (#9) 1861 (Box 54)
  - Notebook of John B. Minor (#10) 1862-1866 (Box 54)
  - Autograph album of Mary Minor (#11) 1862-1866 (Box 55)
  - Notebook of Mary L. Minor (#12) 1865-1866 (Box 55)
  - Wastebook of Mary L. Minor (#13) 1876, 1893 (Box 55)
  - Autograph album of Susan Colston Wilson (#14) 1878-1882 (Box 55)
  - Notebook of Susan Colston Wilson (#15) 1879 (Box 55)
  - Journal and notebook of John Wilson (#16) 1879-1882 (Box 55)
  - Notebook of Susan Colston Wilson (#17) 1883 (Box 55)
  - Scrapbook of Raleigh C. Minor (#18) 1889-1903 (Box 55)
  - Bankbook of Susan Minor Wilson (#19) 1895 (Box 55)
  - Notebook of Susan Colston Minor Wilson (#20) 1899-1901 (Box 55)
  - Diary of Susan Colston Wilson (#21) 1910 (Box 55)
  - Unfinished genealogy of the Minor and Wilson families by Susan Colston Wilson (#22) n.d. (Box 56)
  - Memoranda book of Mary L. Minor (#23) n.d. (Box 56)
  - Casebook [of John B. Minor] (#24) n.d. (Box 56)
  - Materials pulled from bound volumes 1815-1904, 3 folders (Box 56)
- Series VII: Oversize
  - Certificate enrolling John B. Minor in the Literary Society of Kenyon College 1831 Sept. (Box 56)
  - Diploma of John B. Minor, School of Chemistry, University of Virginia 1833 July 18 (Box 56)
  - To the General Assembly of Virginia from the Tennessee Railroad ( Fincastle Democrat Extra) 1838 (Box 56)
  - Safe conduct pass for U.S. ship of war Levant under the command of Capt. L.M. Goldsborough with 20 cannons and 200 man crew. Permission to port at Minorca. 1853 Jan. 3 (Box 56)
  - Photostatic copy of newsclippings re obituary of Benjamin Blake Minor (Richmond News Leader) 1905 Aug. 1 (Box 56)
  - Photostatic copy of newsclippings re obituary of Benjamin Blake Minor (Richmond Evening Journal) 1905 Aug. 1 (Box 56)
  - Broadside, "President Wilson's War Address to Congress" 1917 Apr. 2 (Box 56)
  - Confederate States, Richmond - $5.00 and $20.00 bills (Acc. NO. 38-602) 1864, Money Tray (Box 56)